Nicholas Muchelemba

Solwezi, 10101 | +260971442814 | nmuchelemba60@gmail.com

CAREER OBJECTIVE

Knowledgeable Software Developer with in-depth knowledge of Java, C# JavaScript, Python and PHP. Skilful in developing, optimising and reworking systems to meet specific customer requirements. Expertise in writing codes in various languages, developing flowcharts and layouts and integrating software components.

CORE COMPETENCIES

- Fluent in Java, Python, C#,PHP
- SQL expert
- Drone Programming
- Web development

- Computer Vision
- Project management
- Blazor and Asp.net
- Data Science and AI

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

First Quantum Minerals

Software Developer, April 2021 – Present

- Developing and designing mining related applications using C# (Blazor) with Microsoft Sql server database back end.
- Designing reports in power bi and SQL Server Reporting Services (SSRS).
- Task Automation using python.
- Machine learning to enhance data prediction of mining BCMs and Polygon data.
- Azure DevOps management

National Institute of Public Administration

Software Developer, Oct 2020 – April 2021

- Developing and designing the Online registration module, to be integrated on the student management system.
- Implemented and tested features requested to improve product functionality and extend performance.
- Designed user-friendly software interfaces to simplify overall management.
- Introduced automation tools to reduce redundancy and enhance workflow.
- Technologies used include: PHP, JavaScript, Java, JSP, Python.

Global Drone Academy

Software Engineer/Drone Instructor (part time), Jul 2020–Apr 2021

- Writing Python scripts to automate the drone operation.
- Training students on how to safely fly drones and the safety regulations related to drone operation.
- Training students on how to build drones.

Zambia Industrial Commercial Bank

Information Technology Intern, Aug 2020 – Oct 2020

- Digitised User Request and Change Request Systems using ASP.net core (C#).
- Provide support, Error Tracing, Log management Database Administration on the Oracle Database Platform.
- Manage and provide support for Sea Bank Reports (System) Support and manage IT support
- integration with Jira service desk
- Kept software patched and licences up to date.
- Increased number of resolved job tickets by 50% over previous year.

EDUCATION

Mulungushi University Kabwe

Bachelor of Science: Computer Science, Nov 2020

- Summa cum laude (Distinction) graduate
- Best Graduating Student
- Dissertation: Crop disease detection using machine learning
- ICTAZ Member
- ICTAZ Mulungushi University Chapter Vice President

CERTIFICATION

- Huawei Certification (Routing & Switching HCIA): valid through January 14 2023
- Responsive Web Design (FreeCodeCamp)

ADDITIONAL SKILLS

- Unity Game Developer
- Drone pilot and drone Instructor (Global Air Drone Academy)

WEBSITES, PORTFOLIOS, PROFILES

LINKEDIN: https://www.linkedin.com/in/nicholas-muchelemba/

PORTFOLIO: http://nicholas-muchelemba.herokuapp.com

GITHUB: http://github.com/nicholas124

REFERENCES

Mining Engineer – First Quantum mining Operation(FQMO)

• Name: Mr Niza Mwasile

Tel: +260962890718/0976607529Email: Niza.Mwasile@fqml.com

Head of Department Computer Science - National Institute of Public Administration(NIPA)

• Name: Dr Christopher Chembe Phd.

• **Tel**: +260972890297

• Email: cchembe@nipa.ac.zm

Manager Information Technology (Supervisor) - Zambia Industrial Commercial Bank

• Name: Mr Funwell Malake

Tel: +260966855355

• Email: Funwell.Malake@zicb.co.zm

Co-founder (Supervisor) - Global Drone Academy

• Name: Mr Eno Umoh

• **Tel**: + 1 443-986-7503/+234-902-020-6099

Email: eumoh@gadacademy.org